All right, welcome to Business Central
2026 release wave one
launch edition. This session is about
enhanced analysis mode. My name is Kenny
Pontepedra. I am super proud to have
Blanca with me here as co-speaker. Yes,
thank you, Kenny. So, I'm Blanca and I'm
a software engineer for the developer
experience team.
Awesome. And Blanca is going to show you
and awesome demo
a a few in a few minutes. So, why are we
investing in analysis mode?
Because it's the most used analysis
feature in Business Central
ever.
Almost
every single customer
have users who use analysis mode and so,
we want to make it just smarter to
deploy apps that also use analysis mode
and just have built-in insights to just
make the the application feel like it
has built-in more built-in capabilities
for analytics. So, the highlights of
this is you can ship analysis views from
your AL apps, but also as a user you can
describe your AL
your your views and they will show up as
tool tips.
Um and then we are adding
using these capabilities to also add
analysis tabs or in a few select places
in the Business Central application.
So, the first part support for analysis
views in Excel. Sorry, in AL.
Um
Basically, it should be as simple as 1 2
3.
One, you go to a Business Central, set
up your analysis view directly. Two, you
export that into a JSON file and three
you put that into your app, plug on some
AL demo data or sorry metadata
and that's it. So, why don't you have
why don't we have Blanca show this uh
with a live demo. Blanca, over to you.
So, let's get now some hands in so we
can show you how this feature is used so
you can also package your own analysis
views within your own extensions.
So, the first thing I have here my
Business Central
and then I'm going to open the customer
ledger entries
list page and you can see here I'm
already in analysis mode.
Here you can see different views and
more specifically here I have created
the one that I want to export. Um and
this is a view that just has some
overview information about the different
volumes sales volumes for customers.
One thing that you have also that I have
also added here is the tool tip. So,
here I have provided a description of
these views so that when users get it
they have more context about this view.
And this is the new feature that we have
added this release. To set it can just
go to rename
and then here you will get a description
box where you can just set that
description and then save it.
So
now this is the my view is ready and I
want to package this one in my app.
So, to do so I can just go to share
and I will find this new action export
definition.
And this one over here
will have downloaded a
JSON file.
This is the definition for my analysis
view.
Here I have all the information for my
analysis view. So, I have the name, I
have the tool tip, I have the columns,
all filters or groupings that I have
done in my view are here.
Okay. So, to include this in my app I
already have my project ready here
and then I just need to
put it as part of my project.
And then here in this case I'm just
creating a page extension for my
customer ledger entries.
And here we have added some new syntax
for these pages.
So, now you can define analysis views
and this is where I can define my new
analysis view
and the important part is the definition
file property.
Here I will point the path to the file
that I have just downloaded.
And then I can also set some additional
properties such as the caption or the
tool tip or also the visibility which
will override the settings in the JSON
file.
Um and another interesting scenario is
that you can also use this for page
customizations.
So, let's say for example I have some
analysis views that I want just for
those users who have a specific role.
So, in this case I have created some
analysis views for the accountant.
So, for this I can create a page
customization and then I can just create
a profile
or profile extension and here I can
assign this customization to the
accountant profile.
This way this views are only available
for this profile.
And then
just for completeness this is also
available for source pages of course.
So, if you have some list pages and you
want to add analysis views then you also
have a section where you can do so.
So, that was basically it. It's very
straightforward. So, now we can just go
ahead and publish this extension to a
new environment so you can see how these
are um available in that new
environment.
Yes. So, this is my new environment. You
can see I'm in the customer ledger
entries list page and I have my view
that comes from my app.
You can see this is an a view that comes
from my app because it has this locked
icon.
So, this basically means that I cannot
really edit this view.
You can see the filter pane is gone. You
cannot really sort or anything so this
view is just read only.
But if you want to do some data analysis
on top of this view then you can always
go ahead
duplicate that one
and then this is yours to edit as you
want.
And then
we can also check out the profile
role
the accountant role, sorry.
And then you will be able to see that I
also have those analysis views that I
have defined for this specific profile.
Um another thing is that maybe users
when they have these apps installed they
have many analysis views. Maybe they
decide some of the views are not really
that useful um so they can always go
into personalization mode.
And then you can they can click here and
they can choose to hide that one.
So, then when they are done with it it
will no longer show up.
Blanca, thank you so much for that. Both
the great demo, but also you are
actually the one who brought all of
these features to life.
So, I think all of our 50,000 customers
and many many thousand partners are
going to thank you for all the good
things you do in this space. So
super cool. So, to conclude this session
just wanted to show that we also
using this new these new capabilities in
the Business Central application adding
analysis views to a few areas sales,
auditing finance, inventory and
purchasing. These are coming in 28.x.
So, for sales we aim to have
analysis views on sales orders
on for security related pages
on the change log entries and on the
user lists
on finance on the GL register and fixed
asset ledgers
and on inventory on the item ledger
entries. On purchasing also on the item
ledger entries. So, hopefully this will
kind of light up analysis
mode in the application even for
completely new users.
If you want to learn more there are kind
of two areas here. One is the developer
focus. If you go to aka.ms/bcdeveloper
and and go here in side the
documentation for pages and then
packaging analysis views. That's the new
documentation for all the new AL
features.
If you wanted look at this from the
business side of a functional side
aka.ms/bcanalytics
well is the landing page where you can
then navigate down to
analyze with analysis mode as well as ad
hoc analysis by functional area. Those
two is is showcasing analysis mode for
the users and also with examples more
examples that what we are shipping now
with Business Central out of the box. If
you like this content you might also
like a lot of other related sessions in
this launch edition down here in the
description you can find links to all of
these. Anything from sales analytics,
inventory, finance
finance national reporting, subscription
billing analytics, also Power BI, Excel
and and demo data.
So, with that
myself me myself and Blanca uh want to
say thank you so much for watching our
launch edition video on analysis mode.
We hope you like it because we are not
going to redo it. So, uh
stay tuned. Thank you. And uh we have
some more information on general
resources if you don't know those. Thank
you.
We have compiled a number of general
resources that we believe are key both
for partners but also uh Business
Central customers. Most Some of these
are partner, some of them are also for
customers. So, the first one is
called aka.ms/bcall.
This is a partner resource for that
contains lists of every other aka link
that is needed for you to understand
anything about both the Business Central
product but also processes around it.
We call these aka links because they're
called aka.ms and then for forward slash
something. And with Business Central
links, we all always prefix with BC and
then something.
The next one is uh our uh partner
network uh social media for for Business
Central partners, Viva Viva Engage. So,
aka.ms/bcvivaengage
is where you go and interact with other
partners. It's not open for customers.
So, this is where you can ask uh
questions, interact with the product
group, interact with with with each
other uh in a in a closed network.
Second link A third link is for both
partners and customers. We are called
office hours. So, office hours is
something we do
once or twice a month from the product
group engaging with the community about
new features or things we want to
discuss. aka.ms/bcofficehours
is the is the uh place where you go to
find out about upcoming events.
These are recorded. I believe the
recordings are available only to
partners, but the live events are
available to customers as well.
Fourth link is YouTube our YouTube
channel. I'll talk about that
in the next slide and LinkedIn in the
next slide.
Uh and then finally uh for for Microsoft
partners, uh the BC's uh
aka.ms/bcpartnerportal
is where you get um a a lot of the
resources as a partner such as compete
decks, uh pitch decks, and a lot of
other resources.
For LinkedIn, this is our product
group's uh LinkedIn profile. We have 30K
or more followers. So, both partners and
customers. This is the place where we
from the product group put in news and
small bits of information outside the
official channel. So, follow us
on on LinkedIn to learn what's happening
right now um in in this in the around
the product.
Um and then
uh also on our YouTube channel where
this is where you're probably watching
this aka.ms/bcyoutube.
We put in not only these launch editions
twice a year but also
Copilot and AI video shorts, tips and
tricks, technical deep dives, under the
hood.
Uh we even have this what's cooking
where we put little nuggets of of videos
out for new features that are even
coming in on the YouTube channel before
uh they're coming in the release notes.
So, watch
uh and maybe uh bookmark us on YouTube.
And also notice all the playlists. So,
uh the content is also organized in
areas, not only all the videos. So, if
you have an area that's has special
interest such as analytics,
um you can find an
a playlist and kind of see all the
content related to that.
And that's it. That is truly it. We
won't uh there will be no more. So,
thank you for watching all the way to
the end.
And uh again, have a great day. Thank
you.